[SPEAKER_01]: I just think, yeah, maybe there are a lot of people start with the intention of, basically, the criteria is like, yeah, I have a stressful life, I want to get into meditation because, yeah, I want to find
[SPEAKER_01]: Something which will bring you peace, pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the minute that there's this existential anxiety that comes to the surface that I've been running away from, whenever this... then there's something wrong, then I'm not doing it right, then I need to double down, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, see, and like, as I say that often, you know, especially when I'm criticizing techniques and Goenka and Vipassana and modern time.
[SPEAKER_02]: In itself, it's not a problem if you know why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you generally need to calm down from a stressful life, yeah, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do your yoga, relax, stretch, meditate, watch your breath.
[SPEAKER_02]: But don't confuse that to be the dhamma, because it's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But many people would sort of... many people arrive at this, like, I need to be free from stress, but I don't really want to, you know, significantly impact or give up my life.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's fine, but be clear about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what they arrive then is like, oh, yeah, fine, you don't have to give it up, and you don't have to do any of this, and yes, you are practicing, see what these suttas are teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then they develop this view that, okay, so nothing has to change for me, and I can be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And because of that, they will never understand what real dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because again, they already conflated it, and by thinking that, you know, that it is something that it isn't, you will stop trying to find out what it actually is, because you think you found it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's always the issue with all the methods and techniques.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just... they never amount to, practically speaking, to more than just, you know, calming realization, de-stressing yourself, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's nowhere near.
[SPEAKER_02]: The peace that the Buddha teaches about, the peace of... it's like peace of being unable to suffer amid suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't matter whether you watch your nostrils or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether you are being chopped limb by limb by highway robbers or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're unable to suffer because your mind's free from craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you overcome it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your mind has become so strong that, yeah, it's unable to be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when the Buddha talks about meditation, he talks about purifying mind from the unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_02]: He does not talk about calming.
[SPEAKER_02]: Calmness comes on account of being unable to be disturbed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not on account of calm, calm, on top of the disturbance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or calm, so that I can get disturbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to face the disturbance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to let it endure, so then, on account of it, become strong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now, a person actually can remain clear about their choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, I started this thing because I want to be free from stress, but actually,
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I think...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think I want to give everything up and be fully, completely beyond the possibility of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now I can actually... and they would commit to it rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: They would stop doing their stress-release techniques, and they actually would start taking the teaching seriously, without conflating the two.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because people take the teaching seriously by doing the stress-relief techniques.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they just no longer are able to see the possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they think that... and that's like the
[SPEAKER_02]: So, as long as things are not conflated, yeah, make your own choices, do what you like.
[SPEAKER_02]: But... and then you realize the most you can do is at least just clarifying the choice for people.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, whether they like it or not doesn't matter, at least
[SPEAKER_02]: On some level, they recognize that there might be a choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: As opposed to, yeah, yeah, this is it.
[SPEAKER_02]: We all teach the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That keeps the authenticity... the possibility of authenticity alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: At least...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not doing it now, but I know...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on life support, but at least it's still plugged in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And like you were saying the other day, like, during the time of the Buddha, there were people who would disrobe, and just out of this understanding that, like, yeah, I can't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by admitting that it's on me, they're still keeping this possibility that there is a more authentic path available alive, rather than saying, oh no, the dharma is wrong, and then they no longer have that possibility available to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means that even people who failed,
[SPEAKER_02]: ...and disrobed, who failed the teaching, who failed to fulfill it, still actually develop some wisdom, because they still see... they were still able to at least understand what the practice was.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why they were saying, no, no, no, it was us who were weak, it wasn't the teaching, it wasn't the teacher, and then they would still respect it, and still be virtuous, and still come keeping the eight precepts, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they actually did develop the clarity, and they recognize, okay, no, I don't, I don't, I don't feel like going that far, and they accept the responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't use it as an excuse.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, like, if things were, you know, to go wrong in their life, they would still feel the weight of their responsibility for not freeing themselves from that life in its entirety.
[SPEAKER_02]: They wouldn't lie.
[SPEAKER_02]: They would be unable to lie to themselves about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the disrobed people of the Buddha's time,
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you're unable to be dishonest with yourself, it doesn't matter what threat of pain will, you know, come as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are remaining on the basis where the dhamma is practiced, even if you gave up that time.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, yeah, there were cases that, what, citta, hatha, sariputta, six times he disrobed, and then returned, and then disrobed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because he was authentic enough, that although he failed, he reckoned, and then go back, and six... and after six times he became an arahant, after six ordinations, eventually.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he was doing the work throughout these comings and goings,
[SPEAKER_02]: And, obviously, he was a bit more impulsive, but, fundamentally, he wasn't covering up his actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when he disrobed, he felt the weight of it, he felt the guilt of it, he felt the burden of it, he felt the pointlessness of it, and then went back, and failed again.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, still, never covered it up, which is why, eventually, he succeeded.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not covering it up, you would just see, okay, I'm responsible for this suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, every time that you're putting yourself in that liability, you will just learn more and more, because you're not having... Yeah, by enduring the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because that's why people would cover it up, because it's unpleasant otherwise.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know if I said this when I told you that story of, like, meditating more, but it was similar.
[SPEAKER_02]: When I sort of discovered the suttas and started reading them more and more, it sort of...
[SPEAKER_02]: It kind of clicked that, okay, if there's anything to be right in this world, as far as these teachings in philosophy go, this seems like it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, at the same time, it was also clear to me, okay, so I found what is right.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that part of me was satisfied.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's my choice now to either follow it or just remain enjoying this conviction that this is right.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, immediately, my mind itself, like, considered, okay, so, if I don't follow this, whatever happens to me for the remaining, you know, years of my life, whether it's objectively my fault or not, it's going to be my fault internally, subjectively, because I have not... well, I've chosen, clearly, to not follow the way out.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I've chosen to stay in the environment where things can go one way or the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that environment is the environment of saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, I realize, okay, well, that's not the burden I can live with.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you realize things are objectively, factually out of your hands.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now, imagine you feel responsible for things being out of your hands.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, that's not a pleasant state to live in.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you... and that's exactly when Buddha says, when a man discovers suffering correctly, there are only two possible outcomes of that pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either mental derangement or, no, no, no, I got to do something about this noble search.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you think you manage it, you won't.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're going to be overrun and basically buried under stress and breakdowns and everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or you can actually do something about it before all of that happens.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, at least that's what became clear to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then it was it wasn't even an option anymore, so to speak, for me to whether to become a monk or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was like just when.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, well, if anything's worth doing, it's trying to feel safe from the liability to suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which anything else you could possibly do...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's gonna be within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, again, people are willing to accept that deal for as long as they don't recognize that it's still a matter of their choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you know, I might be fine in this house because I don't realize that the roof is on fire and it's about to collapse.
[SPEAKER_02]: However, if somehow I realize the roof is on fire, I can still choose to stay in the house and enjoy the company and everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if that roof comes... or when that roof comes crashing, I can't blame anybody else.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't even blame the one that started the fire.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I had all the options to apply myself to find the escape.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I've chosen not to.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what became clear to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: That the roof is on fire.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, I don't have to do this, but if I don't do it, I have absolutely no excuse.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if I, again, virtuous, if I do everything right for the rest of my life, sickness, aging and death will have to come to you, to what's yours, things around you, and that will all be on me, because I have not found a way out of the crashing, burning building.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, plain as a day.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not a pleasant thing, but at least it was clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Four Noble Truths, I see as noble, or like the highest or the ultimate, because that is... because all intentions are contained within this desire to come out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they are like... you cannot have an intention outside of... No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...of that intention to come out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you're saying is, basically,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have no choice but to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's then, how do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you act out of it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you act, like, by... Are you acting in a way that results by adding more fuel?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or are you acting in a way that's actually, you know, bringing you closer to understand it and stop fueling it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Which set of other ways?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I act out of craving or do I act to understand the nature of craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: These are the two paths.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Initially, it's all rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: But craving can be abandoned by the means of craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of craving, now you're not acting out as much.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are actually restraining yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're enduring more.
[SPEAKER_02]: All of that does not fuel craving as much.
[SPEAKER_02]: All of that brings it closer to understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because obviously, the more you're able to withstand it, endure it, that impulse to act out out of greed or anger and so on, well, the closer to it you become.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you can see what needs to be seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: Certain aspects of it, certain characteristics will become visible then, because...
[SPEAKER_02]: They're not immediately covered up, usually through, like, just giving in to the desire, or giving in to lashing out, and... or giving in to distraction and indolence and oblivion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the craving is allowed to endure.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're able to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...get to know it a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Familiarize.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or simply, see, by enduring it, you're actually teaching yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: To recognize that, oh, so it does not need to be act upon immediately.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because even that is not apparent to people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even that is not seen as a choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I don't know what to do, but at least I know that I don't have to do anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Per se.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, yeah, this is unpleasant to endure, but that's one thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Acting out will be then seen, oh, but that's a separate thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: I used to think that's just one reaction, but the fact that I can endure it, means, okay, so there's a possibility that it does not need to be acted out of.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you come to see...
[SPEAKER_01]: That that implies this, and now that is very risky, or that is very dangerous.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, then the whole parallel is between, and the relationship will become even clearer, of course.